O. T. Barck Historical Lithograph and Manuscript Collection
O. T. Barck Historical Lithograph and Manuscript Collection
undated
Barck, Oscar Theodore, Jr., 1902-1993.
1 linear ft.
Collection of engravings, lithographs, prints, etc. depicting American historical and literary figures and American historical events, and a small amount of historical manuscript material.
3178209
Biographical History
Oscar Theodore Barck (1902- ) was a professor of American history at Syracuse University, the author of several books on the subject, and a collector of prints and engravings depicting important American historical and literary figures and events.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The O. T. Barck Historical Lithograph and Manuscript Collection consists of engravings, lithographs, prints, etc. depicting American historical and literary figures and American historical events. Subjects range from the American Revolution (e.g., Battle of Long Island, tearing down of the statue of King George III, capture of Fort Ticonderoga), presidents of the United States, American authors (e.g., James Fenimore Cooper, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Washington Irving, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow), and locations (e.g. Mount Vernon, Christ Church in Alexandria, Old Witch House in Salem). There is also a small amount of historical manuscript material -- deeds, indentures, commissions, etc.
Arrangement of the Collection
Original order, as received from donor.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Barck, Oscar Theodore, Jr., 1902-1993.; American literature.; Authors, American -- Pictorial representations.; United States -- History.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Pictorial representations.; Deeds.; Engravings (prints); Financial records.; Indentures.; Lithographs.; Newspapers.; Prints (visual works); Wills.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of O. T. Barck, 1969, 1971.
Inventory
- Action engravings
  - 1. Major Andre making caricatures of American officers, reproduction of a painting
  - 2. The capture of Major John Andre, reproduction of a painting
  - 3. The capture of Andre, engraving
  - 4. Capture of Andre, engraving
  - 5. Capture of Andre
  - 6. Last moments of Major Andre
  - 7. Major Andre, von drey America nern angehalten zu Tarrytown am 23ten September 1780
  - 8. The unfortunate death of Major Andre
  - 9. Treason of Arnold
  - 10. Harvey Birch's warning [ ] Wharton
  - 11. Tearing down statue of George III
  - 12. Battle of Long Island
  - 13. Miss McCrea taken by the bandits
  - 14. Battle of Saratoga. Gen. Arnold wounded in the attack on the Hessian redoubt
  - 15. Saratoga, battleground at Stillwatter [sic]
  - 16. Mrs. Schuyler firing her cornfields on the approach of the British
  - 17. Storming of Stony Point
  - 18. Capture of Fort Ticonderoga
  - 19. Capture of Fort Ticonderoga
  - 20. Capture of Fort Ticonderoga
  - 21. Capture of Fort Ticonderoga
  - 22. Incident in Cherry Valley - Fate of Jane Wells
  - 23. Indian massacre at Wilkes-Barre
  - 24. Massacre of Wyoming
- Group portraits
  - 1. General Horatio Gates; Brigadier-General Philip van Cortlandt, photogravures
  - 2. Washington; Tho. [ ] Warton; Wolfe; Walcot; West
  - 3. Washington and Harvey Birch
  - 4. Our presidents misc.
  - 5. The presidents of our great republic
  - 6. Jefferson; Adams, J.; Monroe; Washington; Madison; Jackson
  - 7. The presidents of the United States
  - 8. The presidents of the United States
  - 9. The presidents of the United States
  - 10. The presidents of the United States
  - 11. Washington; Glive; Hastings
  - 12. L'Amerique
  - 13. The New York Mirror
  - 14. A portrait gallery
  - 15. Bishops
- Portraits
  - 1. Washington Allston
  - 2. Major John Andre
  - 3. John Andre; Albert [ ] [ ]euthal, print
  - 4. Mrs. Benedict Arnold and child, nee Margaret Shippen, portrait
  - 5. Der Americanische Gener. Arnold
  - 6. Arnold, General de l'armee Americanine
  - 7. Le General Arnold
  - 8. George Bancroft, painting
  - 9. Benedict Arnold
  - 10. Barlow, J.
  - 11. Bryant, William Cullen
  - 12. Lt. Gen. Burgoyne
  - 13. Chevalier de Chastellux
  - 14. DeWitt Clinton, material prints
  - 15. Sir Henry Clinton K.B.
  - 16. Sir Henry Clinton
  - 17. General James Clinton
  - 18. J. Fenimore Cooper, painting
  - 19. J. Fenimore Cooper
  - 20. J. Fenimore Cooper
  - 21. R. Waldo Emerson
  - 22. William Floyd of New York 1734-1821
  - 23. Peter Francisco, painting
  - 24. General Horatio Gates, reproduction pencil drawing
  - 25. Fitz Greene Halleck, reproduction painting
  - 26. Hamilton, reproduction painting
  - 27. Hamilton, reproduction painting
  - 28. Alexander Hamilton, print
  - 29. Alexander Hamilton, reproduction print
  - 30. Alexander Hamilton
  - 31. Alexander Hamilton, reproduction print
  - 32. Alexander Hamilton
  - 33. Alexander Hamilton
  - 34. Alexander Hamilton
  - 35. H. Hamlin
  - 36. J. Hancock
  - 37. Oliver Wendell Holmes
  - 38. Washington Irving
  - 39. Washington Irving, reproduction print
  - 40. Washington Irving, reproduction painting
  - 41. T. Jefferson, photogravures
  - 42. Wm. Johnson, negative, three prints
  - 43. M. le M. de La Fayette
  - 44. John Laurence
  - 45. Robert R. Livingston
  - 46. Henry W. Longfellow, reproduction painting
  - 47. Henry W. Longfellow
  - 48. Malher
  - 49. Sam J. B. Morse, reproduction painting
  - 50. J. Lothrup Motley
  - 51. Valentine Mott
  - 52. John Paulding, reproduction painting
  - 53. John Paulding
  - 54. W. Peale, reproduction painting
  - 55. N. H. Prescott, reproduction painting
  - 56. N. Rochester
  - 57. Comfort Sands
  - 58. Maj. Gen. Phillip Schuyler, reproduction print
  - 59. Philip Schuyler Esq.
  - 50. William H. Seward, reproduction print
  - 51. William H. Seward
  - 52. Lydia Huntley Sigourney
  - 53. W. Gilmore Simms
  - 54. Gilbert Charles Stuart
  - 55. Gilbert Charles Stuart
  - 56. Maj. Gen. Sullivan
  - 57. Maj. Gen. John Sullivan
  - 58. Brig. Gen. Anthony Wayne
  - 59. Isaac van Wart
  - 60. David Williams
  - 61. Daniel Webster
  - 62. Daniel Webster
  - 63. Daniel Webster
  - 64. Daniel Webster
  - 65. Noah Webster, reproduction painting
  - 66. Hon. Gideon Welles
  - 67. William White, reproduction painting
  - 68. Eli Whitney
  - 69. W. P. Willis
  - 70. Martha Wilson
  - 71. John Greenleaf Whittier
  - 72. William Wirt
  - 73. Maj. Gen. John E. Wool
- Artwork, miscellaneous
  - 1. Souvenir of 1876
  - 2. Souvenir of 1876
  - 3. [house with trees]
  - 4. [house with trees]
  - 5. [church with trees]
  - 6. Old Swedes Church
  - 7. Mount Vernon, the home of Washington
  - 8. Christ Church, Alexandria
  - 9. Arlington Heights near Washington
  - 10. Last of the old witch house, Salem, Massachusetts
  - 11. The house of David Burnes, standing in 17th St., Washington
  - 12. The monument of Major Andre
  - 13. A letter of B. Arnold, reprint
  - 14. Facsimile of Major Andre's miniature
  - 15. Plan des forts, batteries et poste de West Point 1780
  - 16. Route of Andre
- Documents
  - Deed, Woodbridge NJ, 7 Apr 1672
  - Deed, 7 Jun 1676
  - Fictitious military order with spurious signature of G. Wsahington, Cambridge, 10 Jul 1775
  - Certificate from Peter Van der Lyn, Surgeon to Regiment of Levies, 6 Sep 1786
  - Note to Gen. James Clinton, New Windsor, 13 Nov 1776
  - Note to James Clinton from surgeon in Col. Graham's regiment, 24 Jul 1778
  - Morning report of Capt. James Hasbrouck's company, under command of Gen. James Clinton, 24 Oct 1775
  - Two reciepts to Timothy Pickering, 1783
  - Certificate to Gen. James Clinton, 22 Feb 1787
  - Notice of public freeholders of town of New Windsor, 18 Apr 1796; one of the signers is Robert Burnett, believed to be the last surviving officer of the Revolution and related to Moses DeWitt Burnet
  - Letter to Benson Lossing, Washington, 4 Sep 1775
  - Order for arrest, signed by Henry Livingston, Poughkeepsie, 5 Jan 1776
  - Order for arrest, 23 May 1740
  - Animadversions etc. by Stephen East, 1779; printed by Samuel Loudon at Fishkill
  - Envelope containing colonial currency
  - Receipt signed by Samuel Loudon, 21 Mar 1783
  - Indenture signed by Loudon, 7 Jul 1785
  - Receipt from Loudon, 30 Jan 1783
  - Account book of Robert Burnet, 1800
  - Bond of Hope temperance pledge and anti-tobacco, 1 Sep 1861
  - IOU to President and Fellows of Yale, 4 Jan 1832
  - Problems of fence viewers of town of New Windsor, 13 May 1866; with revenue stamp
  - Letter from Camargo, Mexico re Mexican war, 11 Aug 1846
  - Burnet letter from London, 15 Aug 1846
  - Letter to James Clinton from John Cantine, 1 May 1782
  - Gen. Clinton's account, 1791
  - Letter from DeWitt Clinton to brother Charles, 19 Nov 1787
  - Account of articles bought in New York City for Gen. Clinton, 28 Apr 1790
  - Fifty First Anniversary of American Independence, Lake George, 4 Jul 1827; pamphlet
  - Article on Samuel Loudon by A. J. Wall, 1922; signed reprint
  - Fleury in the American Revolution y LeRoy Kimball, 1935; signed
  - The Family Circle, 1870-1873; manuscript of what a farm family (three sisters and a brother) in Orange County did to improve their culture, etc.
  - Will, signed by Edmund Fanning, New York City, 30 Aug 1771
  - Pension voucher from the office of the Bank of the United States, for Robert Burnett re Revolutioary services, 15 Sep 1830
  - A Pension Claim Lawyer Seeks Business, Nathaniel Hatch, Washington DC, 1856
  - Commissioner of Pensions advises veterans how to make application, 1835
  - Charles Tice, artist, presents a bill, 1853
  - Several insurance policies, mid-nineteenth century
  - Six newspapers of Revolutionary period and a copy of London packet, 1773